associated to every matrix there are two
canonical subspaces but a null space of
a column space and this video I want to
figure out what is the dimension of the
null space and what is the dimension of
the column space now we know that
dimension is just the number of basis
vectors and in fact in previous videos
we've actually seen how to figure out a
basis for the null space and a basis for
the column space so you just figure out
those bases and that's gonna be the
dimension so in this video I'm gonna
quickly go through that process and in
the next video we're going to see some
kind of crazy which is how the dimension
of the null space of how the dimension
of the column space actually relate to
each other and are interconnected so
first off dimension of the null space
I'll remind you that the null space is
all the vectors that are killed off by
applying particular matrix a they're all
the vectors where ax is equal to 0 and
my steps to find a basis for this are
number one I want to go and reduce the
matrix so but ax equal to zero I wanna
see maybe like some example like this
where I've got my Augmented majors with
the zero column I'm gonna put it
actually into our our EF form for you
then what I'm going to do as I say that
there's these two free columns are going
to give me variables for that I read off
of the rows they're gonna tell me what
the rows are going to do and I can put
it then into vector format now if you're
not really speedy with this pause the
video and do it yourself carefully but
the point I want to make is this when I
go through the standard process of
Gaussian elimination and back
substitution to put the vectors in
vector form what I get out of it is a
basis for the null space these two
vectors over here they're linearly
independent and indeed they're by
definition going to be spanning all the
vectors since every vector can be
written in this way so that's the basis
so in this case I've got a big sis it's
got two different vectors in it and
since the dimension is going to simply
be the number of basis vectors the
dimension of the null space is going to
be 2 here so my steps are number one to
reduce the matrix as we just saw number
two to note that the number of free
variables is the same thing as the
number of basis vectors and then we can
say that
dimension of the null space is just
going to be whatever the number of free
variables is going to be so that's
dimension of the null space what about
dimension of the column space now well
what's the column space remember it is
the span of the cause of matrix a and
indeed because the basis has to both
span and be literally independent the
only thing to check in the column space
is the move your independent part cuz it
gets a span part for free so if I take
my matrix like here's the same a I want
to reduce it in the exact same way
because here's the trick if I look at
the first and second column here well
there are multiples of each other
the second column is just twice the
first column so this if I look at all
four vectors they're not linearly
independent however if I focus just on
the vectors with leading ones that still
spans it and that are going to be
linearly independent so the color
leading ones are going to be my basis
for the column space and therefore the
dimension of the column space is just
going to be the number of leading what's
now in the next video what we're gonna
see is we've got the dimension of the
column space we've got the dimension of
the null space but in fact they are
intimately related